Guide to the John Ruskin Letters to Ellen Heaton
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
- Letters from John Ruskin to Ellen Heaton, Ruskin, John, 1819-1900
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1857 late February; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 sheet (2 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.69)
    Ruskin says he enjoys looking at the Calais Heaton sent him as well as the two "blues" [the drawings on blue paper mentioned in Ruskin's previous letter], saying he will keep the latter for a week or two before exchanging them on Heaton's behalf. He asks if a "fine, late, finished [Turner] work" will be acceptable to Heaton in an exchange. Ruskin asks Heaton about her arrangements to have a Rossetti exhibition in Leeds and expresses his dismay that Rossetti was not admitted into the Watercolor Society. Ruskin tells Heaton he can have her Aldborough sent to her, remarking "I really have too much of your property by me just now - and I want you to have some pleasure out of it yourself." [Date provided by Surtees: Latter half of February 1857]
    Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; Old Water-Colour Society (London, England); Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1857 March?; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.70)
    "I have the notes (both halves) all right and your kind letter. I don't mean to let the sketches go -- I think you will like Ehrenbreitstein it is very wonderful. -- Keep Griffiths receipt -- please, I should lose it. -- They are fraternizing with me at the School of design too -- so I have enough on my hands just now --" [Date provided by Surtees: Friday ? March 1857]
    Great Britain. Department of Science and Art; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1857 March?; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.71)
    "I meant, by sketches, the Post's at Sunset -- and the rock on the coast of Genoa -- & the Ehrenbreitstein all of which are safely yours. The latter are nearly drawings but still hasty: very fine. -- I will have them framed for you -- as well as Aldborough. I am trying various experiments in framing & hope to get them prettily done. -- Nothing can be better than the subject you have chosen of Inchbolds." [Date provided by Surtees: ? March 1857]
    Picture frames and framing; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1857 April?; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 18 x 12 (Box 1, Folder H.72)
    "I have not sent the drawing to Mr Richmonds because I can't bear to send it about till it is framed -- the surface is so delicate. I will get it framed ... I have kept your sketches -- I have no doubt you can easily have them when you come to town -- I am very busy -- bothered with woodcuts for my book for beginners [ The Elements of Drawing ] -- doing them in a hurry -- the etching having got spoiled in biting." [Date provided by Surtees: ? April 1857]
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1857 late April; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 18 x 12 (Box 1, Folder H.73)
    "I have been as naughty as usual -- which is saying much. Please bring St Angelo with you. -- To my horror & disappointment I find that ladies are not to be let in -- on the Society of Arts night [an exhibition of paintings by Thomas Seddon]. I am in a great passion thereat and would not have spoken at all if I had known it." [Date provided by Surtees: End of April 1857]
    Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Castle of St Angelo; Seddon, Thomas, 1821-1856; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1857 May; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 33 x 21 cm (Box 1, Folder H.74)
    "I am not going to let you charge me with inconstancy to some purpose. I don't like the St Angelo, now I have it by me. -- I think nature of some sort is pleasanter though there is magnificent work in the St Angelo. I would offer the St Angelo and Lochmaben to White, if I were you -- for the two vignettes of trees he has had by him so long. Both those are pretty and different from what you have. Write to R. [Rossetti] about St John whenever you like: -- it ought to have been done long ago" In a postscript: "Just call on White. He knows the vignettes, ask him if he'll change. Don't hear of any advance in value but if you could take something else, it might facilitate matters." [Date provided by Surtees: May 1857]
    Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Castle of St Angelo; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; White, David Thomas; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1857 May or June; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (2 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.75)
    Ruskin tells Heaton that White has agreed to exchange Heaton's vignette, with an additional 10 guineas, for Turner's vignette of Rhymer's Glen, or Heaton's vignette, plus an additional 40 guineas, for Turner's Dryburgh Abbey vignette. Ruskin advises to only give an additional 20 guineas if she takes the Dryburgh. Ruskin states that the Rhymer's Glen is exquisite and likely to always have high value but that he is less sure about the Dryburgh as he "suspect[s] the colours a little". Ruskin ends by saying that if she doesn't like the exchange she should wait for a better one but to let White know whether she will accept the offer by the next Monday. [Date provided by Surtees: May or June 1857]
    Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Rhymer's Glen; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Dryburgh Abbey; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; White, David Thomas; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1857 mid-July; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (2 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.76)
    Ruskin gives Heaton some advice on what to see at the Manchester Art Treasures Exhibition, praising works by Paul Veroneses, Joshua Reynolds, William Hogarth, Anthony van Dyck and Thomas Gainsborough. Ruskin thanks Heaton for "all [her] notes.". [Date provided by Surtees: Mid-July 1857]
    Art Treasures Exhibition ( 1857 Manchester, England); Veronese, 1528-1588; Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792; Hogarth, William, 1697-1764; Van Dyck, Anthony, 1599-1641; Gainsborough, Thomas, 1727-1788; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1857 December 7; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.77)
    Ruskin apologizes for not meeting Heaton when she was last in London. Ruskin describes the work he has being doing with regards to the National Gallery's Turner collection, saying he has been kept very busy. Ruskin says he will not prepare more than 1,000 for exhibition in the coming winter. Ruskin describes some of the works as "valueless in England -- but very valuable on the Continent in a few years." He tells Heaton he found "a very precious" sketch book containing "the most lovely designs possible.". Ruskin tells Heaton he continues to enjoy her vignettes and drawings on blue paper and that her Parnassus and Cestius are the most beautiful vignettes he knows. Ruskin says he has sent letter to the Brownings but that they had not replied and so must not have received his letters. Ruskin asks that if Heaton meets them to apologize to them on his behalf. [Date provided by Surtees: 7th December 1857]
    Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Parnassus and Castalian Spring; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Walls of Rome with the Tomb of Caius Sestus; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; National Gallery (Great Britain); Browning, Elizabeth Barrett, 1806-1861; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1858 November; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.78)
    Ruskin says he had hoped to come into town but couldn't manage it. Ruskin says he can't believe that Heaton has returned home and is preparing to travel again in the time since they last met. Ruskin expresses his envy that Heaton was able to see the Brownings, remarking that he had sent a letter to Elizabeth Barrett Browning a month ago but that he has no time to write letters at the moment. He asks Heaton to send his love to the Brownings and to tell them that he will write to them soon, asking Heaton to send him a letter when she sees them to tell them how they are. Ruskin asks Heaton if he can take charge of her Turners. Ruskin says the last volume of Modern Painters is taking shape and that he is contemplating writing an essay on how to distinguish good poetry from bad and muses that Robert Browning might have some ideas that would be useful on the matter. Ruskin gives his best wishes for Heaton's journey and tells her that he has been reading some of her writing lately. He says he has not seen the Richmonds since he has been home and asks Heaton to pass on his love to them. [Date provided by Surtees: November 1858]
    Browning, Elizabeth Barrett, 1806-1861; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; Richmond, Thomas, 1802-1874; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1859 June 2; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter signed; 21 x 26 cm; 21 x 14 cm (Box 1, Folder H.80)
    Ruskin tells Heaton to go to Griffiths at Norwood and look at the "body colour drawings" in his collection. Ruskin says he had not exchanged Heaton's drawings, believing better drawing to be in Griffith's collection. Ruskin suggests she wait a while before buying anything as Griffith has been raising his prices. Ruskin tells her not to worry if she does not receive this letter while still in London as the drawings will not sell quickly due to a "depression in the Turner market." Ruskin thanks Heaton for "the ultramarine" and for her help. Ruskin says that he has visited Rome, travelling via Brussels, not Paris. Ruskin admits he is only writing in order to try to catch Heaton in London but that, generally, he has given up writing letters.
    Griffith, Thomas, active 1831-1869; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1860 mid-April?; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 18 x 20 cm, folded to 18 x 10 cm (Box 1, Folder H.87)
    "Just read enclosed, and if you can call tomorrow to look at Drawing -- and give Hunt [i.e. William Henry Hunt?] my love and say I hope to get places at theatre directly for next week. -- Beautiful photographs. I shall choose the leaf cave and another not cascatelles with best thanks - - Love to Mr & Mrs Richmond & children -- I hope I shall hear all are well." [Date provided by Surtees: ? Mid-April 1860]
    Hunt, William Henry, 1790-1864; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1860 December 14; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 26 x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder H.90)
    "I like Hughes Picture exceedingly -- It is not Auroro Leigh in the least but you cannot expect a young man -- happy in wife & family -- & full of exceeding tenderness -- to understand the fiery depths of stormy Sunrise. This picture is a charming one of two people in love. It has its faults of course -- but you are fortunate in possessing it. Your Mystery is Arles, on the Rhone." [Date provided by postmark: 14 December 1860]
    Hughes, Arthur, 1832-1915. Aurora Leigh's Dismissal of Romney; Hughes, Arthur, 1832-1915; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1861 April?; Royal Institution of Great Britain; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.92)
    "I can't send my drawings to the Faraday night [Michael Faraday lectured at the Royal Institution on 3 May 1861] -- Fashionable people are a mere mob -- Send 'em acorns if you like -- not pearls." In a postscript, Ruskin writes: "When you come to town as you first intended it will do nicely." [Date provided by Surtees: ? April 1861]
    Faraday, Michael, 1791-1867; Royal Institution of Great Britain; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1861 late April?; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.93)
    "We will see about your private ticket [presumably for the Royal Academy]. I send you Turner -- with sincerest thanks. -- You can't conceive how worried I am just now about dozens of things -- & and can't call nor see people -- anyhow. I shall have to run out of town again I fancy.". In a postscript, Ruskin writes: "My main work is in arranging the Cambridge collection of sketches & very difficult." [On May 28, 1861, Ruskin presented 25 Turner watercolors to the Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge.] [Date provided by Surtees: ? End of April 1861]
    Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; Royal Academy of Arts (Great Britain); Fitzwilliam Museum; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1861 May 22; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.95)
    "Ive written to somebody who will send you tickets for anything at the college ticketable [presumably the Working Men's College]. I shall not be saying or doing anything anywhere these ten years." [Date provided by postmark: 22 May 1861]
    Working Men's College (London, England); Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1861 early June; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 5 sheets: 1 folded (4 pages); 4 sheets (4 pages): autograph letters signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm; 6 x 12 cm; 8 x 12 cm; 6 x 12 cm; 5 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.96)
    Ruskin has sent Heaton four duplications of the signatures from letters he has sent to his father (these are the four sheets additional to the primary, folded letter). Ruskin describes a "leaf drawing" (of Alpine rose leaves) which contains qualities not found in the work of the Pre-Raphaelite Brotherhood, "namely lusciousness and (not terrific) gloom" which Ruskin describes as more "Correggioesque than most modern work." Ruskin complains that he could have written 50 guineas worth of writing in the time it took him to find the work, which is worth no more than £20. Ruskin says he cannot bring himself to sell the work for more than it is worth but refuses to sell it for less than it cost him in lost writing time and thus concludes that he cannot sell it. Ruskin tells Heaton he has no desire to give his work to charity and that he always thought he would exchange any pieces which became valuable for other artworks and that he might one day complete such an exchange for the "leaves" with Heaton. Ruskin tells Heaton he will be taking on no further speaking arrangements after his lecture about French Architecture to the Ecclesiological Society. Heaton says that he does not think the society admits women but that he will tell Heaton if they do. Ruskin thanks Heaton for her account of Adelaide Ironside, whom Heaton has recently met. Ruskin tells Heaton that William Morris's The Defence of Guenevere is published by Bell & Daldy. The four additional signature sheets all contain the following proceeded by Ruskin's signature: "Dearest love to my Mother Every my dearest Father Your most aff. son." [Date provided by Surtees: Beginning of June 1861]
    Pre-Raphaelite Brotherhood; Ironside, Adelaide, 1831-1867; Morris, William, 1834-1896; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1862 late April?; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.109)
    "I'm so sorry -- but not even the Alpine rose drawing will be available just now for we want all we can get on the walls to replace the Turners which are to be shut up during great exhibition [the South Kensington International Exhibition] to avoid bore of various sorts -- and I can't part with any of my late sketches, which are all unfinished and good for nothing. I'm to talk nowhere -- and can talk about nothing -- but I'll try and answer any questions you have for me before I leave town -- love to Mr Richmond -- delighted to see him tomorrow." [Date provided by Surtees: Probably end of April 1862]
    Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; International Exhibition (1862: London, England); Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1862 early May; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 sheet (2 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.110)
    Ruskin says he "has nothing to say for [himself] so [he] won't say it." Ruskin tells Heaton that prior to receiving her letter saying she did not like Edward Burne-Jones's work, Ruskin had asked the artist for some works for her, including a piece for twenty guineas. Ruskin states that Jones will not give him any of the works if he thinks the recipient doesn't really want them but that he "depends" upon the sale and so Ruskin asks if Heaton could take one for the time being. Ruskin says that Jones is only likely to show his works to close friends so Ruskin had to choose a work on Heaton's behalf but promises to "clear [Heaton] of the picture in due time.". [Date provided by Surtees: First part of May 1862]
    Burne-Jones, Edward Coley, 1833-1898; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1862 late November?; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 sheet (2 pages): autograph letter signed; 32 x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder H.112)
    Ruskin tells Heaton that he's feeling better but still unable to talk to anyone. He tells Heaton he has her Hughes work ( That was a Piedmontese ) and praises the work as "exquisitely beautiful in the face of the woman." Ruskin vows to never criticize work by a living man but goes on to say that Hughes has not been true to Elizabeth Barret Browning's poem A Court Lady by failing to make the subject's dress grand enough. Ruskin admonishes Heaton for being "absurd to think [she] knew better about literature or anything else than Rossetti." Ruskin says he will "relieve" Heaton of her Jones work and suggests that he will buy her a "pretty" picture of Jones's which the artist produced to raise money for "Manchester starving people." Ruskin enquires whether Turner's Ehrenbreitstein is at the home of Thomas Richmond and admits he has "a plan about it -- can't tell [Heaton] to day.". [Date provided by Surtees: Probably latter half of November 1862]
    Hughes, Arthur, 1832-1915. That was a Piedmontese; Hughes, Arthur, 1832-1915; Browning, Elizabeth Barrett, 1806-1861; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1864 May 1?; item; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (2 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.119)
    "I carried off the Dream (Rossetti's Dante's Dream ) from Chelsea only two day's before my father's death; so that my promise to Rossetti to photograph it was ... roughly hindered -- I shall be glad that you undertake it -- as I was afraid to take it out of the frame -- you shall have it in a week -- and never let it out of your power more" (Ruskin's father died 3 March 1864 and this letter has a mourning border.) Ruskin goes on to thank Heaton for her offer of Turner's Cestius but admits that he cannot make use of it at the moment - he will ask her for it if he would like it in the future. [Date provided by Surtees: c. May 1st 1864]
    Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Dante's dream at the time of the death of Beatrice; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Walls of Rome with the Tomb of Caius Sestus; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882
- Miscellaneous
  Arrangement
  The collection is arranged into two series: I. Letters from John Ruskin to Ellen Heaton; II. Miscellaneous. The letters are arranged chronologically.
  - Lines of verse from Psalms and Proverbs, 1850 July 18; item; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (1 page); 25 x 20 cm, folded to 13 x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder add.1)
    "The sea is His – and He made it, and His hands prepared the dry Land./(By His Knowledge the depths are broken up, and the clouds drop down the dew.)/Oh come, let us worship & bow down and kneel before the Lord our maker." (Psalms 95:5-6; Proverbs 3:20.) Signed: "John Ruskin, July 18th, 1850."
    Bible -- Quotations
  - John Ruskin letter to Thomas Richmond, 1850s?; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder add.2)
    "Can you favour us at six, Wednesday 1 June with your company to dinner and oblige?"
    Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence; Richmond, Thomas, 1802-1874 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Thomas Richmond, 1856 or 1857?; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder add.3)
    "I shall be delighted to look at the Mont Blancs, for my own personal pleasure no less than for all other reasons, but you don't tell me the name of the artist, nor when I can see them. I am coming to see you very soon bringing Miss Heaton's glorious drawing with me -- Aldbourough. I hope you will enjoy it -- when you can look at it constantly and easily. Love to you all. I am sincerely sorry to hear of your continued illness."
    Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence; Richmond, Thomas, 1802-1874 -- Correspondence; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894
  - Ellen Heaton letter to her family, 1858 October 20; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894; 1 sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 18 x 11 cm (Box 1, Folder add.4)
    "I wish these letters by John Ruskin, Esq. to be preserved, if they should any of them be though suitable to be published in a selection from his letters in some Life eventually written to commemorate him. I shall be glad that they should be used in that way. I hope my nieces and nephews may be interested in these letters, and preserve them."
    Ruskin, John, 1819-1900